Photographs from the Mary Margaret McBride Collection
Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress
Photographs from the Mary Margaret McBride Collection, 1934-1968, and undated
McBride, Mary Margaret, 1899-1976
3 boxes, including approximately 620 photographic prints, 23 negatives, and 15 folders of textual material
Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Photographs and accompanying paper documents that form part of the much larger Mary Margaret McBride Collection in the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division of the Library of Congress. The collection represents McBride's long and influential career as a journalist and pioneering woman radio personality; photographs show McBride, some of her guests, program anniversary events, and featured places and products.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bradley, Omar Nelson, 1893-1981--Photographs.; McBride, Mary Margaret, 1899-1976--Photographs.; McBride, Mary Margaret, 1899-1976.
Subjects
Radio broadcasting--United States--Photographs.; Radio talk shows--United States.; Women in radio broadcasting--United States.
Form/Genre
Negatives.; Photographic prints.; Portrait photographs.; Publicity photographs.
Occupations
Women journalists--United States--Photographs.; Women radio producers and directors--United States--Photographs.; Women radio talk show hosts--United States--Photographs.
Administrative Information
Collection Acquisition
The Mary Margaret McBride Collection, which includes these photographs, was a gift to the Library of Congress from Cynthia Lowry, McBride's long-time friend, in 1977.
Additions
No further additions to the collection are expected.
Access Restrictions
The Photographs from the Mary Margaret McBride Collection are open for research.
Biographical Note
Mary Margaret McBride (1899-1976) was a journalist and the host of an immensely popular daily radio program from the mid 1930s into the 1950s. Her first program, Martha Deane, was broadcast on station WOR from 1934 until 1940. In 1937 CBS hired her to host a fifteen-minute talk show under her own name, but her most popular program, a forty-five-minute interview and talk show on NBC, ran from 1941 until 1950.
McBride's daily program featured interviews with over twelve hundred leading public and political figures of her time, such as entertainers, other radio personalities, authors, educators, doctors, and adventurers, but she also talked with average people who had interesting stories to tell. Interviewees included Eleanor Roosevelt, Governor Thomas E. Dewey, Frank Lloyd Wright, Bob Hope, Carl Sandburg, Margaret Bourke-White, Zora Neale Hurston, Tennessee Williams, Joe DiMaggio, a man leading a campaign to improve teenage driving skills, a female test pilot, the woman who invented crossword puzzles, and the American Mother of 1942.
McBride's interviews provide a highly personal perspective on American life during the Great Depression through World War II, its aftermath, and the beginning of the Cold War. They constituted the first thirty minutes of her show and were followed by informal discussion of household matters and advertising. Commercials were targeted at McBride's primary audience -- women -- who eagerly purchased the products she promoted and made McBride a favorite with sponsors. Her popularity with listeners and sponsors alike allowed her to retain both editorial and commercial control of her program.
McBride moved to ABC in 1950. She died on April 7, 1976, at age 76.
Scope and Content Note
The photographs and accompanying paper documents form part of the much larger Mary Margaret McBride Collection, 1935-1950, in the Recorded Sound Section of the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress. Representing McBride's long and influential career as a pioneering woman radio journalist, the McBride Collection includes over twelve hundred hours of interview programs and other radio broadcasts. The photographs include portrait, publicity, and family photographs of Mary Margaret McBride; pictures of McBride and her guests, such as Omar Bradley, Mike Wallace, Eleanore Roosevelt, Thomas Dewey, and Mary Martin; shots of her radio program's anniversary celebrations; images relating to her 1960 autobiography, Out of the Air and of various products and locations; and depictions of broadcasting both in and outside of the studio.
Collection Arrangement
The photographs and accompanying documents are arranged by file.
http://lccn.loc.gov/2008647476
Container List
- Mary Margaret McBride with Stella Karn (Estelle), undated, 5 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Stella Karn was McBride's manager.
- Paper documents accompanying the Mary Margaret McBride and Stella Karn photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1A)
- McBride publicity photographs, undated, 16 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Early McBride portrait photographs, undated, 12 photographic prints, 2 negatives: black and white (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Paper documents accompanying the early McBride portrait photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4A)
- McBride portrait photographs, undated, 12 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 1, Folder 5)
- McBride portrait photographs with microphone, undated, 9 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 6)
  WEAF/NBC.
- McBride portrait photographs with microphone, undated, 5 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 1, Folder 7)
  CBS.
- McBride portrait photographs with microphone, undated, 14 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 8)
  WNBC/NBC.
- McBride portrait photographs with microphone, undated, 1 photographic print: black and white (Box 1, Folder 9)
  ABC/WJZ.
- Miscellaneous McBride portrait photographs, undated, 7 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 10)
- McBride color portrait photograph, undated, 1 photographic print: color (Box 1, Folder 11)
- McBride personal appearance photographs, 1934-1951, 11 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 12)
- McBride personal appearance photographs, 1957-1968, undated, 8 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 1, Folder 13)
- McBride with Eleanor Roosevelt, undated, 6 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 1, Folder 14)
- McBride with Governor Thomas Dewey, undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 15)
- McBride with Omar Bradley, undated, 10 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride and Omar Bradley photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16A)
- McBride with political guests, undated, 13 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 17)
- McBride with guests, undated, 5 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 1, Folder 18)
- McBride with Mary Martin, undated, 4 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 19)
- McBride with guest authors, undated, 6 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride and guest author photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20A)
- McBride with special guests, undated, 17 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 21)
- McBride with unidentified guests, undated, 1 photographic print: black and white (Box 1, Folder 22)
- McBride with groups, undated, 15 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride with groups photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23A)
- McBride receiving awards, undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 24)
- McBride cooking with Poppy Cannon, Paul and Grace Hartman, undated, 6 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 25)
- McBride with Tex and Jinx, Bob Hope, undated, 4 photographic prints: black and white (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride, Tex and Jinx, Bob Hope photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26A)
- McBride with Mike Wallace, undated, 8 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 27)
- McBride radio anniversaries: Martha Deane, undated, 7 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 28)
- McBride radio anniversaries: Madison Square Garden, undated, 8 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 29)
- McBride radio anniversaries: Yankee Stadium, undated, 5 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 30)
- McBride radio anniversaries: unidentified, undated, 9 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 31)
- McBride Out of the Air, undated, 33 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
- Paper documents accompanying the Out of the Air photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 33A)
- McBride and Eve Curie, undated, 1 negative (Box 2, Folder 34)
- McBride radio anniversaries: white dress, undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 35)
- McBride photographs relating to Florida citrus fruit, undated, 8 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 36)
- McBride photographs relating to Florida, winter haven, undated, 10 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride Florida, winter haven photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 37A)
- McBride with doll collection, undated, 4 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 38)
- McBride Laffing Room Only photographs, [1944 or 1945], 13 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 39)
- McBride Maine photographs, undated, 9 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride Maine photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 40A)
- McBride Mexico, Missouri parade, undated, 14 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 41)
- McBride Mexico, Missouri photographs, undated, 14 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride Mexico, Missouri photographs, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 42A)
- McBride small Mexico, Missouri photographs, undated, 10 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 43)
- McBride at William Woods College photographs, undated, 2 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 44)
- McBride New Jersey photographs, 1938, 11 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride New Jersey photographs, 1938, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 45A)
- McBride Seabrook Farms, New Jersey, photographs undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 46)
- McBride, The French Goat photographs, undated, 6 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 47)
- McBride, Jackson & Perkins, MMM Rose, undated, 9 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 48)
- McBride at the Dwight D. Eisenhower arrival parade, [1945?], 4 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 49)
- McBride military tour photographs, undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 50)
- McBride European visit photographs, undated, 7 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 2, Folder 51)
- McBride bagpipes photographs, undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 52)
- McBride and animals, undated, 7 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 53)
- McBride backyard broadcasting photographs, 1951, 6 photographic prints: black and white (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Paper documents accompanying the McBride backyard broadcasting photographs, 1951, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 54A)
- McBride broadcasting in locations other than the studio, undated, 8 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 55)
- McBride eating and cooking, undated, 13 photographic prints, 3 negatives: black and white (Box 3, Folder 56)
- McBride with unidentified guests, undated, 3 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 57)
- McBride and unidentified guests with microphones, WOR, CBS, WEAF, NBC, and ABC, undated, 16 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 3, Folder 58)
- McBride's last broadcast, 1954, 22 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 3, Folder 59-60)
- McBride on television, undated, 8 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 61)
- McBride Conti Shampoo commercial, undated, 17 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 3, Folder 62)
- McBride's retirement, undated, 14 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 63)
- McBride personal and family photographs, undated, 20 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 64-65)
- McBride personal and family photographs, undated, 26 photographic prints: color (Box 3, Folder 66-67)
- McBride at a dinner with Harry Truman and others, undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Paper documents accompanying the photos of McBride at a dinner with Harry Truman and others, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 68A)
- McBride at home, undated, 7 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 69)
- Unidentified McBride photographs, small, undated, 11 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 70)
- Unidentified McBride photographs, undated, 10 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 71)
- McBride in the studio with a group, undated, 1 photographic print: black and white (Box 3, Folder 72)
- McBride at a dinner in Connecticut, undated, 6 photographic prints, 1 negative: black and white (Box 3, Folder 73)
- Paper documents accompanying the photographs of McBride at a dinner in Connecticut, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 73A)
- McBride at Bette Davis's birthday party, undated, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 74)
- McBride at the christening of the USS Matthews, 1944, 5 photographic prints: black and white (Box 3, Folder 75)
- Paper documents accompanying the photographs of McBride at the christening of the USS Matthews, 1944, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 75A)
Additional Guides
Access to individual descriptions of the audio recordings in the Mary Margaret McBride Collection is available through the SONIC recordings catalog of the
Recorded Sound Reference Center
. Click on Recorded Sound Catalog (SONIC) and search by guest name or date of broadcast.
McBride Papers
The Papers of Mary Margaret McBride, 1926-1975, are available in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress. Consisting of correspondence, articles, clippings, printed material, photographs, and other papers pertaining chiefly to her career in journalism, the papers were transferred from the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division in 1980. A finding aid to the papers is available in the Manuscript Division Reading Room.